<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://scs.community/feed/release.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://scs.community/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2022-05-19T09:56:51+00:00</updated><id>https://scs.community/feed/release.xml</id><title type="html">Sovereign Cloud Stack | Release</title><subtitle>Sovereign Cloud Stack (SCS) is a network of existing and future providers of standardized sovereign cloud and container infrastructure to join forces in defining, implementing and operating a fully open, federated, compatible platform. By joining forces, the platform can support a healthy ecosystem for service and application developers and strengthen the digitalization efforts in Europe without creating large risks to lose control over the technology and the data.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">SCS R2 released</title><link href="https://scs.community/release/2022/03/22/release2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SCS R2 released" /><published>2022-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-19T09:53:48+00:00</updated><id>https://scs.community/release/2022/03/22/release2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://scs.community/release/2022/03/22/release2/"><![CDATA[<p>The Sovereign Cloud Stack project, funded by the <a href="https://www.bmwi.de/Navigation/EN/Home/home.html">German Federal Ministry for Economic Affairs
and Climate Action</a> will release
its third version of the SCS reference implementation R2 on March 23, 2022. 
Highlights of Release 2, to whose success a community of over 20 companies have 
contributed are updates of the integrated open source components, the simplified
deployment on bare metal, significantly improved management of Kubernetes clusters,
as well as the technical foundations for connecting to the <a href="https://www.gxfs.eu/">Gaia-X Federation Services (GXFS)</a>.</p>

<p>Defined and implemented in an open development process, the technology of <a href="https://scs.community/de/">Sovereign
Cloud Stack (SCS)</a> is being tested by a growing
number of companies and public IT service providers. In addition, two (soon three)
providers are already using SCS in production environments to offer public cloud
services. The C5 certification of our partner <a href="https://www.plusserver.com/en/">PlusServer</a>
also proves that the Sovereign Cloud Stack meets the high security requirements
of the <a href="https://www.bsi.bund.de/EN/Home">German Federal Office for Information Security (BSI)</a>.</p>

<p>By participating in the working groups of <a href="https://www.gaia-x.eu/">Gaia-X</a> and
the <a href="https://www.cio.bund.de/Web/DE/Innovative-Vorhaben/Deutsche-Verwaltungscloud-Strategie/deutsche_verwaltungscloud_strategie_node.html">Deutsche Verwaltungscloud-Strategie (DVS)</a> 
the Sovereign Cloud Stack project ensures that the project’s jointly developed
standards and reference implementation also meet the requirements from these key
initiatives. The Sovereign Cloud Stack thus forms not only a technical foundation
for Gaia-X compliant infrastructure, but also for a resilient, federatable public
sector cloud.</p>

<p>The key points for Release 3, due in the fall of 2022, will be the completion of the
disk encryption feature, the expansion of federation capabilities, and the development
of fully automated SCS conformance tests. The latter are intended to enable already
established cloud service providers to adapt and validate their own offerings to the
established SCS standards.</p>

<p>The goal of Sovereign Cloud Stack is to develop a fully open-source toolkit for
sovereign, standardized cloud &amp; container infrastructure. Consumers of such
infrastructure can thus painlessly manage services across multiple SCS-compliant
offerings.</p>

<blockquote><p>
Through open source, open standards, and
an open development process, Sovereign Cloud Stack makes an important contribution
to minimize lock-in effects in the cloud business, creating freedom of choice and thus
strengthening the progress of digitalization in Europe - with full control over
technology and data.
</p><cite>Peter Ganten, Chairman of the Board of the Open Source Business Alliance e.V.</cite>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="technical-highlights-in-scs-release-2">Technical highlights in SCS Release 2</h2>

<p>In detail, the following technical highlights, among others, were realized with Release 2:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Update of core components to OpenStack Xena, OSISM 3.0.0, and Kubernetes Cluster
API 1.0.x with added support for Kubernetes 1.22 and 1.23.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Automation of bare metal deployment has been massively extended. The configuration
of the components is now managed by NetBox as central source of truth. This means
that setups with a high number of machines can be deployed with a manageable
operational effort.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Kubernetes Cluster API-based automation for managing Kubernetes clusters is
now designed to manage many differently configured clusters. Clusters can now be
created in different projects and availability zones and are also independent of
each other’s configuration. This allows for different Kubernetes versions, different
network integration (CNI), different numbers and flavors of machines as well as an
independent selection of standard services. The configuration can be maintained in a
git repository.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Standard services within Kubernetes container management have been extended by
flux (gitops) and cert-manager (certificate management), the ingress-nginx has
been enhanced and cilium can now be used instead of calico for the
cluster network integration.
DevOps teams thus do not have to worry about integration of these components.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The quality of our stack is constantly assured by conformance tests
of the Cloud Native Computing Foundation and the Open Infrastructure Foundation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The SCS standards for image metadata and machine flavor naming published with
Release 1 have been fully implemented. Thus, it is easier to develop automated
installations (Infrastructure-as-Code) without having to deal with numerous
little differences for different cloud offerings.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The required components to connect to the Gaia-X Federation Services (GXFS)
have been completed. The Gaia-X Federation Services will allow to connect the
various Gaia-X services. Thus, a very important milestone of SCS for Gaia-X has
been reached.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/Docs/blob/main/Release-Notes/Release2.md">full release notes</a>
will be available on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/Docs/">https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/Docs/</a>
as of Wednesday.</p>

<h2 id="about-sovereign-cloud-stack">About Sovereign Cloud Stack</h2>

<p>The Sovereign Cloud Stack (SCS) was launched in 2019 and initially funded by the
Federal Agency for Disruptive Innovations - SPRIND. Since July 2021, SCS is a
project of the Open Source Business Alliance and receives funding by the German
Federal Ministry for Economic Affairs and Climate Action (BMWK, formerly BMWi).
A growing community of more than 20 companies contribute to the success of Sovereign
Cloud Stack. By joining forces, standards for a modern, federatable open source
cloud and container platform are defined and implemented by using proven open source
components. At the same time, operational knowledge and <nobr>practices</nobr> are
transparently shared to minimize the difficulty of delivering high-quality and secure
cloud offerings. Two (soon three) providers are already using SCS in production
environments to offer public cloud services. Further setups are in the development
and testing phases.</p>

<h2 id="about-the-open-source-business-alliance-osb-alliance">About the Open Source Business Alliance (OSB Alliance)</h2>

<p>The Open Source Business Alliance (OSB Alliance) is the association of the open
source industry in Germany. We represent over 170 member companies that employ
approximately 10,000 people and generate more than 1.7 billion euros annually
in Germany. Together with scientific institutions and user organisations, we
are committed to sustainably anchoring the central importance of open source
software and open standards for a successful digital transformation in the
public awareness. This digital transformation should benefit companies, the
state and society alike. In addition, innovations in the field of open source
should be promoted. Our goal is to establish open source as the standard in
public procurement and in research and business promotion. After all, open
source and open standards are essential foundations for digital sovereignty,
innovative capacity and security in the digital transformation and thus the
answer to one of the greatest challenges of our time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Sovereign Cloud Stack</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Sovereign Cloud Stack project, funded by the German Federal Ministry for Economic Affairs and Climate Action will release its third version of the SCS reference implementation R2 on March 23, 2022. Highlights of Release 2, to whose success a community of over 20 companies have contributed are updates of the integrated open source components, the simplified deployment on bare metal, significantly improved management of Kubernetes clusters, as well as the technical foundations for connecting to the Gaia-X Federation Services (GXFS).]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://scs.community/assets/images/blog/pile.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://scs.community/assets/images/blog/pile.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SCS R1 released</title><link href="https://scs.community/release/2021/10/05/release1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SCS R1 released" /><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-19T09:53:48+00:00</updated><id>https://scs.community/release/2021/10/05/release1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://scs.community/release/2021/10/05/release1/"><![CDATA[<p>After R0 has been released in July and focused on the installation of a <a href="https://docs.osism.tech/testbed/">test environment</a>, the release R1 of Sovereign Cloud Stack was released last Wednesday, 2021-09-29.</p>

<p>The newest release R1 includes the <a href="https://releases.openstack.org/wallaby/">OpenStack Wallaby Release</a>, <a href="https://github.com/kubernetes/kubernetes/releases">Kubernetes version v1.21.x</a>, and the <a href="https://github.com/kubernetes-sigs/cluster-api/releases">Kubernetes Cluster API version v0.4</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/Docs/blob/main/Release-Notes/Release1.md">full release notes</a> including technical details can be found in the <a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/Docs">central docs repository</a> of the SCS project on GitHub.</p>

<h2 id="kubernetes-cluster-as-self-service-thanks-to-cluster-api">Kubernetes cluster as self-service thanks to cluster API</h2>

<p>A special focus during this sprint was on the management of Kubernetes containers based on the k8s Cluster API, which was integrated in version Alpha 4. Both through the conformance tests of the <a href="https://www.cncf.io/">Cloud Native Computing Foundation</a> using <a href="https://sonobuoy.io/">sonobouy</a>, and in real-world use during the <a href="https://www.gaia-x.eu/news/gaia-x-hackathon-1-new-technology-develops-live-today-and-tomorrow">first Gaia-X Hackathon</a> on August 30 and 31, 2021, the maturity of SCS’s k8s cluster management was tested and determined for productive systems.</p>

<figure class="figure mx-auto d-block" style="width:90%">
  <a href="/assets/images/release1/screenshot-capi-provisioning-k9s.png">
    <img src="/assets/images/release1/screenshot-capi-provisioning-k9s.png" class="figure-img w-100" />
  </a>
    <figcaption class="figure-caption">
    Kubernetes cluster can be deployed on-the-fly through the k8s cluster API.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>With the Kubernetes Cluster API, DevOps teams can create and manage Kubernetes clusters for development, for test and staging, and for production environments on-thy-fly. Of course, the cloud operator can also offer a managed service to its users via the same technology. Detailed <a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/k8s-cluster-api-provider/blob/master/Release-Notes-R1.md">release information on SCS’s k8s-cluster-api-provider</a> can be found in the <a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/k8s-cluster-api-provider">corresponding repository</a>.</p>

<h2 id="sovereign-operation-through-monitoring-and-logging">Sovereign operation through monitoring and logging</h2>

<p>The Sovereign Cloud Stack project’s Monitoring Special Interest Group has collected <a href="https://github.com/osism/kolla-operations">various examples of monitoring SCS environments</a>. The blueprints for Prometheus exporter, rules and Grafana dashboards can be used by providers after appropriate customization to ensure low-threshold, high-quality operation of their own SCS platform.</p>

<figure class="figure mx-auto d-block" style="width:90%">
  <a href="/assets/images/release1/screenshot-ceph-dashboard.png">
    <img src="/assets/images/release1/screenshot-ceph-dashboard.png" class="figure-img w-100" />
  </a>
    <figcaption class="figure-caption">
    With R1, easy-to-use dashboards are available.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For the upcoming release, we plan to integrate these blueprints directly into the testbed deployment and also make them available to the OpenStack upstream community. We particularly welcome feedback on the examples integrated in release R1 and, in addition, suggestions on other essential operational tools.</p>

<p>With the current version of OSISM in release R1, centralized logging is now also enabled by default. The logging rules still have to be adapted by the provider according to his environment. Similar to monitoring, we also plan to publish already tested rules in the area of logging as a blueprint with the upcoming releases.</p>

<h2 id="a-federated-and-secure-data-platform">A federated and secure data platform</h2>

<p>Authentication against Horizon, the OpenStack standard web interface for using an SCS Cloud, can additionally be realized with <a href="https://openid.net/connect/">OpenID Connect</a> via the integrated identity and access management solution Keycloak. This enables federation across multiple cloud service providers, in line with the vision of Gaia-X.</p>

<p>For the following release R2, we plan to work further on the high availability of the IAM service, which could not be fully tested at the time of the release in its current implementation based on Galera Cluster.</p>

<h2 id="automated-distribution-on-bare-metal">Automated distribution on bare metal</h2>

<p>For automated distribution of the Sovereign Cloud stack on physical hardware, the <a href="https://ironicbaremetal.org/">ironic</a> service can be installed using OSISM. To enable prior testing of the automated deployment, a virtual BMC service has been integrated, so that bare metal deployments can also be tested in the testbed. The main building blocks are already available upstream, but were not fully integrated into R1 due to the short timing of the release.</p>

<h2 id="further-announcements-about-the-project">Further announcements about the project</h2>

<p>Following the successful engagement of the SCS community in the first Gaia-X Hackathon, concrete plans are already being made for the second Hackathon on December 2 and 3, 2021. This will feature a dedicated two-day session in which a fully sovereign cloud will be built from scratch. Interested cloud architects are invited to join us in installing and running SCS hands-on on real hardware.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/logo-greencis.png" class="float-left" alt="GREEN-CIS" style="width:300px;" /></p>

<p>In addition, as part of the “Important Project of Common European Interest - Cloud Infrastructure and Services” (IPCEI-CIS), the SCS project is actively participating in the so-called GREEN-CIS consortium, short for “General Purpose Resilient and Secure Energy Efficient Computing Infrastructure Network”. This growing alliance of a total of 28 industry and research partners has set itself the goal of developing and building a virtual, sustainable cloud edge system operating as a single entity based on a decentralized, multi-provider ecosystem. In this regard, we are pleased to receive positive feedback from the German Federal Ministry for Economic Affairs and Energy, which will send the GREEN-CIS consortium together with 21 other projects to the European matchmaking event on October 06, 2021.</p>

<p>The Sovereign Cloud Stack project will play a central role as an open and sovereign cloud technology and will serve as the basis for further platform services as well as for a modern edge cloud.</p>]]></content><author><name>Sovereign Cloud Stack</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After R0 has been released in July and focused on the installation of a test environment, the release R1 of Sovereign Cloud Stack was released last Wednesday, 2021-09-29.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://scs.community/assets/images/default-card.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://scs.community/assets/images/default-card.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SCS R0 released</title><link href="https://scs.community/release/2021/07/15/release0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SCS R0 released" /><published>2021-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-19T09:53:48+00:00</updated><id>https://scs.community/release/2021/07/15/release0</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://scs.community/release/2021/07/15/release0/"><![CDATA[<p>With great pleasure, we announce the Release 0 of Sovereign Cloud Stack.</p>

<p>While we officially only got the funding for our project a few days ago, we
have already been able to do very useful work with the community that we were
able to set up and which engaged in collaboratively developing software.</p>

<p>R0 is the culmination of more than a year of work, all of which can be found on
github. <a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/">SCS</a> heavily relies on
<a href="https://github.com/OSISM/">OSISM</a>, so we actually are building on top of
many years of work there. A lot of the SCS work got integrated back into it.
SCS and OSISM of course build on top of thousands of person years
of upstream communities’ work. We are standing on the shoulders of giants.</p>

<p>We are really proud with what we achieved with our volunteer community!  The
automation for the lifecycle management of the (containerized) base
infrastructure, the operations tooling, IAM and the IaaS layer is rock solid.
The first two partners, <a href="https://betacloud.de">betacloud</a> and
<a href="https://www.plusserver.com/en/products/pluscloud">PlusServer</a> are already
using this for their productive clouds and more are in the pipeline.
We have been monitoring the demonstrator (gx-scs) environment from PlusCloudOpen
with <a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/openstack-health-monitor">openstack-health-monitor</a>
and have seen only one slowliness warning in weeks and not a single alarm.
This is no small feat.</p>

<p>Thanks to anyone who contributed to this nice release!</p>

<p>R0 focuses on <a href="https://docs.osism.tech/testbed/">testbed</a> deployments – we
want to make it easy for anyone to use SCS for testing, inspection,
contribution, comparison, inspiration, … at this stage. This in no way should
discourage anyone from a production deployment on bare metal – as mentioned we
have two cloud providers already using it. Exploring testbed is typically the
first stage though. Get in touch with us if you have made yourself familiar
with SCS via testbed already and want to move to the next stage.</p>

<p>We have updated a lot of documents in the last days. Use our
<a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/Docs/">github Docs</a> as entry point.
There are specific
<a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/Docs/blob/main/Release-Notes/Release0.md">release notes for R0</a>.
You can of course also find this from the <a href="/get">“Get SCS”</a>
page from our <a href="">web site</a>.</p>

<p>The documents explain how to perform a testbed installation and also how to use
the Technical Preview pieces such as the Kubernetes aaS pieces using the
<a href="https://github.com/SovereignCloudStack/k8s-cluster-api-provider">k8s-cluster-api</a>.
This will be one of the focus areas for R1 which we already
plan for September. (Note: We’ll have a 6 month release cycle going forward,
though the reality is more continuous than this sounds.)</p>

<p>Let us know if you have questions or feedback. We like github issues and PRs,
but will try to followup on <a href="mailto:project@scs.sovereignit.de">email</a> as well.</p>]]></content><author><name>Sovereign Cloud Stack</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With great pleasure, we announce the Release 0 of Sovereign Cloud Stack.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://scs.community/assets/images/default-card.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://scs.community/assets/images/default-card.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>